<t_visa_cover_letter_guide>
  <introduction>
    <title>Final Cover Letter Template for the T Visa Application</title>
    <section id="purpose_of_cover_letter">
      <question>What is the purpose of the Cover Letter (CL) in a T Visa application?</question>
      <answer>The Cover Letter is a key document that accompanies the application for T Nonimmigrant Status (T Visa) filed with U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services (USCIS). Its purpose is to:</answer>
      <points>
        <point id="summarize">Summarize the case: Clearly and persuasively explain why the applicant meets the legal requirements to obtain the T Visa.</point>
        <point id="guide">Guide the adjudicator: Organize the information and legal arguments, highlighting how the applicant satisfies each eligibility criterion.</point>
        <point id="personalize">Personalize the application: Provide a human and detailed account of the applicant’s experience, supported by evidence, to create empathy and justify approval.</point>
      </points>
      <conclusion>The CL is essential for structuring the case, facilitating USCIS’s review, and increasing the chances of approval.</conclusion>
    </section>
    <section id="t_visa_definition">
      <question>What is the T Visa?</question>
      <answer>The T Visa is a temporary immigration status for victims of severe trafficking in persons, created under the Victims of Trafficking and Violence Protection Act of 2000. It allows applicants to remain in the U.S., work legally, and in some cases, apply for permanent residency. Applicants must demonstrate that:</answer>
      <requirements>
        <requirement>They are victims of severe trafficking.</requirement>
        <requirement>They are in the U.S. due to trafficking.</requirement>
        <requirement>They have cooperated (or are willing to cooperate) with authorities in the investigation of trafficking, unless exempt.</requirement>
        <requirement>They would suffer extreme hardship if deported.</requirement>
        <requirement>They are admissible or qualify for a waiver of inadmissibility.</requirement>
      </requirements>
    </section>
  </introduction>

  <chapter_explanations>
    <title>EXPLANATION OF EACH CHAPTER OF THE COVER LETTER</title>
    <intro_text>The CL presented for Applicant is structured into sections that address each eligibility criterion for the T Visa, along with a request for a waiver of inadmissibility and a conclusion. Below is a detailed breakdown to train your colleagues on writing an effective CL:</intro_text>

    <writing_style>
      <language>en</language>
      <person>third</person>
      <neutral_third_person>true</neutral_third_person>
      <refer_as>the applicant; the declarant; the victim</refer_as>
      <avoid_em_dashes>true</avoid_em_dashes>
      <paragraphs length="extremely_long" target_sentences_per_paragraph="10-14"/>
      <min_total_words>2400</min_total_words>
      <final_letter>true</final_letter>
      <voice>formal persuasive narrative</voice>
      <use_client_quotes>true</use_client_quotes>
      <quote_directives min_quotes="6" multiline="true" attribution_format="[Decl. ¶ {n}]"/>
      <citation_emphasis>narrative_with_limited_inline_cites</citation_emphasis>
      <avoid_training_language>true</avoid_training_language>
      <include_firm_identity>false</include_firm_identity>
    </writing_style>

    <narrative_expansion>
      <task id="A">Summarize the provided text in six paragraphs, written in third-person neutral, referring to the declarant as “the declarant” or “the applicant,” beginning with “The declarant details in the declaration.” Focus primarily on experiences of abuse (physical, verbal, financial, coercive, or others), using multi-line verbatim quotes extracted from relevant sections where the abuse is explicitly mentioned. Briefly summarize the reasons for leaving the country of origin and migrating to the United States in a single paragraph, giving them low priority. Use high-level formal English with precise vocabulary and an empathetic tone that reflects the severity of the abuses. Do not use em dashes.</task>
      <task id="B">Write in English, in third-person neutral, three paragraphs that explain in detail what the person would suffer if forced to return to their country. Describe how this situation would affect the person and their family in all aspects (emotional, economic, social, etc.).</task>
      <task id="C">In three lines, clearly and concisely summarize what the person endured at the hands of their traffickers. This text should be a brief conclusion about their trafficking experience.</task>
      <task id="D">Use the following text as a writing example and reference for key points. Based on the prior information about the case, write a general introductory paragraph about the case without combining information. It should be a very general summary that serves as an introduction.</task>
      <task id="E">Using the person’s information, write a report in English referring to them as “the victim” or “the applicant.” Focus on the abuse suffered at the hands of the traffickers. Summarize in one and a half paragraphs, using the best possible grammar and vocabulary. Include specific details about the locations and circumstances of the trafficking experienced. For dates, mention only the month and year, without specifying day.</task>
    </narrative_expansion>

    

    <template_example>
      <date format="MM/DD/YYYY" label="false"><DATE/></date>
      <header>
        <delivery_method>Via FedEx</delivery_method>
        <address_lines>
          <line1>USCIS Nebraska Service Center</line1>
          <line2>Attn: I-914</line2>
          <line3>850 S St.</line3>
          <line4>Lincoln, NE 68508-1225</line4>
        </address_lines>
      </header>
      <subject_template>RE: {APPLICANT_NAME}, T-1 Principal Applicant{, {DERIVATIVES_LIST}}.</subject_template>
      <subject_casing>preserve</subject_casing>
      <derivative_format>{NAME}, {ROLE}{, {RELATIONSHIP}}</derivative_format>
      <form_reference label="false">I-914 Applicant for T Nonimmigrant Status</form_reference>
      <salutation>Dear T Visa Adjudicator,</salutation>
      <opening_paragraph>
        The Law Offices of Manuel Solis represents <APPLICANT_NAME/> (hereafter, “Applicant”) in <PRONOUN_POSSESSIVE/> immigration matters and now submits <PRONOUN_POSSESSIVE/> application for T nonimmigrant status. Applicant is <AGE/> years old, national of <NATIONALITY/>, and a victim of a severe form of trafficking in persons under the Victims of Trafficking and Violence Protection Act of 2000. INA § 101(a)(15)(T) (as amended); 8 U.S.C. § 1101(a)(15)(T).
      </opening_paragraph>
    </template_example>

    <chapter id="I" title="APPLICANT IS A VICTIM OF A SEVERE FORM OF TRAFFICKING IN PERSONS">
      <purpose>To demonstrate that the applicant suffered severe trafficking, as defined by law (INA § 101(a)(15)(T)).</purpose>
      <content>
        <general_description>Describe the specific facts of exploitation, such as forced labor, confinement, threats, physical, psychological, or sexual abuse.</general_description>
        <case_specific_example>
          <heading>In the case of the Applicant:</heading>
          <point>He was kidnapped in McAllen, Texas by armed traffickers who confiscated his phone, money, and documents.</point>
          <point>He was threatened with firearms, isolated, and forbidden from contacting his family while his release was conditioned on payment of a remaining $3,000 debt.</point>
          <point>He was subjected to a degrading search under the pretext of finding hidden items, and his movements were controlled until his recovery by the original coyotes.</point>
        </case_specific_example>
      </content>
      <drafting_tip>Use clear, compassionate, non-sensational language; prioritize precision. Include specific details (locations, duration, type of abuse) supported by evidence (sworn statements, police reports, psychological evaluations).</drafting_tip>
      <citations>
        <policy ref="System_Prompt.configuration.citation_policy"/>
        <quotes recommended_max="4" multiline="true" min_lines="2" cite_as="[Decl. ¶ {n}]"/>
        <style>inline-short</style>
        <max_inline_citations>3</max_inline_citations>
        <forbid_internal_artifacts>true</forbid_internal_artifacts>
        <artifact_examples>filecite; turnXfileY; tool_anchors</artifact_examples>
      </citations>
      <narrative_requirements>
        <item>Use neutral third-person references ("the applicant", "the declarant").</item>
        <item>Describe specific facts: forced labor, confinement, threats, physical, psychological, or sexual abuse.</item>
        <item>Include locations, approximate durations, and chronology tied to declaration citations.</item>
        <item>Insert 2–4 multi-line verbatim quotes where abuse is explicitly described.</item>
        <item>Maintain trauma-informed, non-sensational tone; prioritize precision and empathy.</item>
        <item>Cross-reference supporting evidence (declaration paragraphs, medical/psychological reports).</item>
        <item>Render facts as integrated narrative; do not output bullet lists or checklists in the final letter.</item>
        <item>Do not recharacterize the family-based assault in Houston as a second trafficking event; present it as post-arrival victimization relevant to hardship and cooperation.</item>
      </narrative_requirements>
      <paragraph_guidance>Compose 3 very long paragraphs weaving facts and quotes to substantiate severe trafficking under INA § 101(a)(15)(T).</paragraph_guidance>
      <length min_words="500" min_paragraphs="3"/>
    </chapter>

    <chapter id="II" title="APPLICANT IS PHYSICALLY PRESENT IN THE U.S. DUE TO TRAFFICKING">
      <purpose>To prove that the applicant’s presence in the U.S. is directly related to trafficking, either because it occurred in the country or because of its ongoing effects.</purpose>
      <content>
        <general_description>Explain how trafficking led the applicant to the U.S. or why he remains due to its effects (trauma, fear of reprisals).</general_description>
        <case_specific_example>
          <heading>In the case of the Applicant:</heading>
          <point>His presence is linked to persistent psychological and emotional trauma caused by trafficking.</point>
          <point>Cite regulation (8 C.F.R. § 214.11(g)) which allows consideration of the ongoing impact of trafficking.</point>
        </case_specific_example>
        <citations>
          <required_citation>[8 C.F.R. § 214.11(g)]</required_citation>
          <quotes recommended_max="4" multiline="true" min_lines="2" cite_as="[Decl. ¶ {n}]"/>
        <style>inline-short</style>
        <max_inline_citations>3</max_inline_citations>
        </citations>
      </content>
      <drafting_tip>Focus on the causal link between trafficking and current presence; cite the regulation. Use at most two brief quotes tied to the declaration.</drafting_tip>
      <narrative_requirements>
        <item>Explain the causal connection between trafficking and current presence in the U.S.</item>
        <item>Emphasize ongoing impacts (trauma, fear of reprisals, safety concerns) consistent with 8 C.F.R. § 214.11(g).</item>
        <item>Use neutral third-person references; avoid inference of gender or honorifics.</item>
        <item>Include 2–4 multi-line quotes illustrating persisting effects, with declaration citations.</item>
        <item>Render facts as integrated narrative; do not output bullet lists or checklists in the final letter.</item>
      </narrative_requirements>
      <paragraph_guidance>Compose 2 very long paragraphs linking facts to 8 C.F.R. § 214.11(g) with concise quotes.</paragraph_guidance>
      <length min_words="300" min_paragraphs="2"/>
    </chapter>

    <chapter id="III" title="APPLICANT HAS COMPLIED WITH REASONABLE REQUESTS FOR ASSISTANCE IN THE INVESTIGATION OF TRAFFICKING">
      <purpose>To show that the applicant has cooperated (or is willing to cooperate) with authorities in investigating or prosecuting traffickers.</purpose>
      <content>
        <general_description>Detail the applicant’s actions, such as reporting the crime, providing information, or being available to assist.</general_description>
        <case_specific_example>
          <heading>In the case of the Applicant:</heading>
          <point>He reported the trafficking to the Department of Justice and expressed his willingness to cooperate fully.</point>
          <point>His bravery in coming forward demonstrates his commitment to justice.</point>
          <point>On August 16, 2025, counsel reported the trafficking to the Department of Justice (Civil Rights Division) and the Texas Attorney General; the applicant remains available to comply with reasonable requests.</point>
          <point>Any delay in reporting is credibly explained by coercive threats and fear of removal, consistent with the trauma and danger considerations in 8 C.F.R. § 214.11(h).</point>
        </case_specific_example>
        <citations>
          <required_citation>[8 C.F.R. § 214.11(h)]</required_citation>
          <quotes recommended_max="4" multiline="true" min_lines="2" cite_as="[Decl. ¶ {n}]"/>
        <style>inline-short</style>
        <max_inline_citations>3</max_inline_citations>
        </citations>
        <exceptions reference="8 C.F.R. § 214.11(h)">age, trauma, danger</exceptions>
      </content>
      <drafting_tip>Highlight cooperation when present; if exceptions apply, explain neutrally with supporting facts and cite the regulation.</drafting_tip>
      <narrative_requirements>
        <item>Detail actions taken: reporting dates, agencies contacted, willingness to assist.</item>
        <item>Reference 8 C.F.R. § 214.11(h); if applicable, note exceptions (age, trauma, danger) neutrally.</item>
        <item>Use neutral third-person references and include 1–3 multi-line quotes illustrating cooperation and the impact of coercion and fear, when present.</item>
        <item>Cross-reference reporting receipts and Supplement B status.</item>
        <item>Render facts as integrated narrative; do not output bullet lists or checklists in the final letter.</item>
      </narrative_requirements>
      <paragraph_guidance>Compose 2 very long paragraphs narrating cooperation history and present availability to assist.</paragraph_guidance>
      <length min_words="300" min_paragraphs="2"/>
    </chapter>

    <chapter id="IV" title="APPLICANT WOULD SUFFER EXTREME HARDSHIP IF REMOVED FROM THE U.S.">
      <purpose>To prove that deportation would cause unusual and severe harm, considering trafficking-specific factors.</purpose>
      <content>
        <general_description>Address factors such as age, mental/physical health, psychological impact of trafficking, risk of re-victimization, lack of support in the home country, and loss of access to justice in the U.S.</general_description>
        <case_specific_example>
          <heading>In the case of the Applicant:</heading>
          <point>He faces a high risk of re-victimization in Honduras; his family has been displaced by gangs and he has previously suffered thefts, underscoring pervasive insecurity.</point>
          <point>He would lose access to the U.S. justice system and the ability to cooperate with investigations relating to his trafficking victimization.</point>
          <point>He would suffer severe economic dislocation; although he works steadily in home remodeling in the United States, comparable opportunities in Honduras are scarce and unsafe.</point>
        </case_specific_example>
        <citations>
          <required_citation>[8 C.F.R. § 214.11(i)]</required_citation>
          <factors_reference>8 C.F.R. § 214.11(i)(2)(i)-(iv), (vi), (vii)</factors_reference>
          <quotes recommended_max="4" multiline="true" min_lines="2" cite_as="[Decl. ¶ {n}]"/>
        <style>inline-short</style>
        <max_inline_citations>3</max_inline_citations>
        </citations>
      </content>
      <drafting_tip>Personalize the arguments and enumerate relevant factors from 8 C.F.R. § 214.11(i)(2).</drafting_tip>
      <narrative_requirements>
        <item>Address hardship factors: age/personal circumstances; medical/psychological conditions; consequences of trafficking; loss of access to U.S. justice; risk of re-victimization; harm likely from traffickers/associates.</item>
        <item>Describe impacts across emotional, economic, social, and safety domains with declaration citations.</item>
        <item>Use 2–4 multi-line quotes illustrating fear, symptoms, or risks, when present in the declaration.</item>
        <item>Maintain neutral third-person; avoid sensational detail.</item>
        <item>Render facts as integrated narrative; do not output bullet lists or checklists in the final letter.</item>
      </narrative_requirements>
      <paragraph_guidance>Compose 4 very long paragraphs explicitly mapping facts to 8 C.F.R. § 214.11(i)(2)(i)–(iv), (vi), (vii).</paragraph_guidance>
      <length min_words="600" min_paragraphs="4"/>
    </chapter>

    <chapter id="V" title="APPLICANT IS ELIGIBLE FOR A WAIVER OF INADMISSIBILITY">
      <purpose>To request a waiver for any grounds of inadmissibility (such as unlawful entry or minor offenses) through Form I-192.</purpose>
      <content>
        <general_description>Explain that the applicant submitted Form I-192 to address possible inadmissibility grounds. Argue that granting the waiver serves the humanitarian and public/national interest, supporting anti-trafficking efforts and victim protection.</general_description>
        <must_cite>INA § 212(d)(3)(B); INA § 212(d)(13)(B)</must_cite>
        <exclusions>Nazi persecutions, genocide, torture, extrajudicial killings</exclusions>
        <case_specific_example>
          <heading>In the case of the Applicant:</heading>
          <point>Cooperation with authorities and role in combating trafficking justify the waiver.</point>
          <point>No involvement in disqualifying activities.</point>
        </case_specific_example>
        <public_national_interest_arguments>
          <point>Approving the waiver enables a victim-cooperator to assist law enforcement in identifying, disrupting, and prosecuting trafficking networks.</point>
          <point>It advances the TVPA’s goals by protecting survivors, encouraging reporting, and preventing re-victimization.</point>
          <point>It promotes public safety and the rule of law through ongoing cooperation with DOJ, DHS, and state authorities.</point>
          <point>It recognizes the applicant’s community contributions, including steady employment and tax compliance, which further the public interest.</point>
        </public_national_interest_arguments>
      </content>
      <drafting_tip>Request the waiver proactively when appropriate; emphasize humanitarian and public interest rationales.</drafting_tip>
      <narrative_requirements>
        <item>State that Form I-192 is submitted (or will be) and identify any known grounds generally.</item>
        <item>Argue humanitarian and public/national interest rationales; highlight cooperation with authorities.</item>
        <item>Affirm no involvement in disqualifying activities.</item>
        <item>Use neutral third-person references.</item>
        <item>Explicitly articulate how the victim-cooperator role advances investigations and prosecutions against traffickers.</item>
        <item>Connect the waiver to TVPA policy goals and broader public safety benefits.</item>
        <item>Render justification as integrated narrative; avoid listing evidence or checklists in the body.</item>
      </narrative_requirements>
      <paragraph_guidance>Compose 1 very long paragraph articulating waiver rationale grounded in INA § 212(d)(3)(B) and § 212(d)(13)(B).</paragraph_guidance>
      <length min_words="220" min_paragraphs="1"/>
    </chapter>

    <chapter id="VI" title="CONCLUSION">
      <purpose>Summarize the arguments, reiterate the request for approval, and provide contact information.</purpose>
      <content>
        <general_description>Reinforce the seriousness of the trafficking suffered and how the applicant meets all criteria. Respectfully request approval of the T Visa and the waiver of inadmissibility.</general_description>
        <case_specific_example>
          <heading>In the case of the Applicant:</heading>
          <point>Summarize his suffering, cooperation, and need for protection.</point>
          <point>Include the attorney’s contact number.</point>
        </case_specific_example>
      </content>
      <drafting_tip>Be brief but impactful. End with a professional and grateful tone.</drafting_tip>
      <narrative_requirements>
        <item>Reinforce satisfaction of all eligibility elements and summarize cooperation and need for protection.</item>
        <item>Respectfully request approval of the T Visa and any requested waiver.</item>
        <item>Provide counsel contact information if appropriate.</item>
        <item>Use neutral third-person references.</item>
      </narrative_requirements>
      <paragraph_guidance>Compose 1 very long paragraph culminating in the specific request.</paragraph_guidance>
      <length min_words="180" min_paragraphs="1"/>
    </chapter>
  </chapter_explanations>

  <conclusion_and_signature>
    <signature_block>
      <closing>Respectfully submitted,</closing>
      <attorney_line><ATTORNEY_NAME/>, Esq.</attorney_line>
      <firm_name>Law Offices of Manuel Solis</firm_name>
      <address><FIRM_ADDRESS/></address>
      <phone><COUNSEL_PHONE/></phone>
      <email><COUNSEL_EMAIL/></email>
    </signature_block>
  </conclusion_and_signature>
</t_visa_cover_letter_guide>